大约一年前 2019年3月中旬 波音737MAX在短短几天之内被全球禁飞
About one year ago, in mid-March, 2019, Boeing's 737 MAX was quickly and unceremoniously grounded.
这件事在很多方面都有深远影响
This was hugely significant in quite a few different ways.
对于波音来说 MAX是他们最畅销的系列机型中的最新款
For Boeing, the MAX was the newest generation of their most popular aircraft series
而这件事给波音原本出色的可靠性与安全性记录带来了巨大污点
and its difficulties place a huge stain on the company's stellar safety and reliability record.
同时 对于美国来说 此事抑制了全国最大的公司之一的发展
Meanwhile, for the US, it halts growth at one of the countries largest companies and employers,
再往远了说 还牵扯到了全球的航空业
and then beyond that, for the worldwide aviation industry,
在全球大多数航司还在不停买这架飞机的时候 此事让387架飞机无法上天
it puts 387 aircraft on the ground at a time of continued growth for most every airline worldwide.
如今 多数人都知道了MAX被禁飞的原因：
Everyone knows why the 737 MAX was grounded by now—
在特定情况下 故障的传感器会给软件传递错误数据
faulty sensors would, in particular circumstances, indicate incorrect information to software
导致软件向飞机发送低头的指令
which would respond by sending the aircraft into a nosedive.
而多数人不太了解的是波音怎样才能让MAX重返蓝天
What's less known is how Boeing will get the 737 MAX flying again.
除了全球禁飞之前的387架飞机之外
In addition to the 387 aircraft that were flying prior to the grounding,
波音在之后九个月还在持续生产MAX
Boeing kept production going for nine months after this
所以现在还有额外400架已经总装好的飞机
so there are about another 400 completely assembled aircraft
就停在波音工厂外每一块空地上
sitting on every empty piece of tarmac outside Boeing's factory.
飞机不是造出来摆着玩的
Aircraft are not built to sit around.
除了偶尔进行的长时间维护
Except for the occasional longer period of maintenance,
多数商业飞机不会有一天“休息”不上天
most commercial aircraft won't go a day in their lives without taking the skies,
而在这起事件中 这些飞机只能在地上停着
but in this case, aircraft will have sat, abandoned,
停上一年多 直到MAX可以重新上天
for more than a year by the time the MAX is cleared to fly again.
让这八百架飞机重新上天是个漫长又复杂的活
The process of getting those 800 aircraft to the skies will not be quick or easy.
让MAX重新上天也不仅仅是让FAA批准波音对飞机的修复
Getting the MAX flying again is also more complicated than just gaining the FAA's approval for their fixes.
一项委托调查显示 有70%的美国旅客表示以后会避免乘坐MAX
One commissioned survey found that 70% of American travelers say they will avoid flying on the MAX,
即使它重新通过认证
even when it is recertified.
波音先要说服管理者这款飞机能飞 然后还要说服公众这款飞机能飞
Boeing has to persuade regulators it can fly, and then it has to persuade the public it can fly.
这需要波音和航司们付出巨大的努力
It will be a massive, monumental effort by the company and the airlines.
关于MAX复飞 我们不了解的第一件事是时间
The first thing that we don't know about the 737 MAX's return is when it will happen.
2019年3月 MAX刚被全球停飞的时候
When it was first grounded back in March 2019,
波音说预计几周就能解禁
Boeing expected the aircraft to be flying again in a matter of weeks.
然后 解禁的日期就一拖再拖一咕再咕
Since then, the date of return has been pushed back and pushed back and pushed back again.
本视频截稿时(2020年2月27日) 波音声称MAX会在2020年中复飞
At the time of writing, Boeing says the aircraft will fly again in mid-2020
但和之前一样 极有可能还会继续延期
but just like every time before, it's quite possible that will slip further.
另一个不了解的事情是从技术角度来看
Another unknown is exactly how, from a technical standpoint,
波音将如何修复这引起两次空难的故障
Boeing will fix the issues that caused the two crashes,
外加停飞以后又冒出来的一堆其他问题
in addition to a number of other issues that have been identified since then.
我们现在已知的是 如果波音找到解决方案 自己满意了
What we know is that, once Boeing is satisfied that it has indeed reached a solution,
那他们会通知FAA安排一次认证飞行
it will notify the FAA and schedule a certification flight.
为了认证 波音会提供一架软硬件部分都进行修复过的MAX飞机
For this, Boeing will provide one 737 MAX aircraft with any and all physical and software tweaks installed,
FAA飞行员会飞它上天 看看这些修复是否完善
and FAA pilots will take to the skies to determine if these fixes are satisfactory.
然后是几天的数据分析 再然后 假如一切修复都符合要求
What will follow is a short, few day analysis period and, assuming the fixes seem to be working,
那么这个流程会转交给联合行动评估委员会（JOEB）
the process will be passed on to the Joint Operations Evaluation Board.
JOEB是FAA下面一个由全世界的MAX飞行员组成的小组
This is a FAA-run group made up primarily of 737 MAX pilots from around the world
他们的工作是确定在驾驶修复后的MAX前需要进行哪些训练
who's job it is to determine what sort of training pilots will need before flying the 737 MAX again.
这些飞行员会现在模拟机中尝试这些修复的部分 从而获得第一手经验
These pilots will each try the fixes in a simulator, in order to have first-hand experience,
之后 大约两周后
and then, after about two weeks,
JOEB会将他们的建议提交给FAA的飞行标准化委员会
the board will pass their recommendation onto the FAA's Flight Standardization Board
后者会将建议整理成一份报告
who will incorporate the recommendations into a report.
而这一步 预计将会对MAX的复飞带来巨大阻碍
It is this step that is expected to establish a tremendous hurtle to the MAX's reentry to service.
因为根据波音的建议 预计FAA将需要先进行模拟机训练
It is expected, on Boeing's recommendation, that the FAA will require simulator training
才能让飞行员驾驶MAX飞机重新上天
before MAX pilots can fly the aircraft again.
这个建议的分量很容易被低估
It'd be easy to underestimate how significant this is.
MAX机型本身设计是希望飞行员不需要进行模拟机培训就能飞
The entire MAX aircraft was designed around assuring that pilots would not need simulator training.
波音想让MAX能无缝适配航司原有的737机组
Boeing wanted the MAX to seamlessly fit into the airlines fleets of older 737 aircraft
这样飞了30年机龄老737的飞行员可以直接去飞MAX
so that the same pilot who flies a 30 year-old 737 can fly a brand new 737 MAX.
因为飞行员培训成本极高 因此减少培训需求就能极大降低运营MAX机队的成本
That's because pilot training is hugely expensive and so a lack of need for it would, by extension,
lower the cost of operating the 737 MAX to airlines.
波音在之前的营销材料中是这么吹的：
Boeing boasted in marketing materials
MAX与NG的通用性
NG和MAX飞行员可无缝切换
·计算机培训和其他视频教程
·无需模拟机训练
时间：机组只需2天或更少
“原737飞行员只需两天的计算机培训就能驾驶MAX”
that it would take only two days of computer based training to certify an existing 737 pilot to fly the MAX.
对降低培训量的需求甚至是催生出MCAS系统的主要原因
The push for limited training was even a major factor behind the implementation of the MCAS system
而MCAS系统正是两起空难的罪魁祸首
that caused the two MAX aircraft to crash.
他们想让MAX飞着感觉和其他的737一样
They wanted the plane to fly like it was any other 737
虽然在没有电子设备的干预下 这俩感觉是不一样的
even though, without electronic intervention, it did not.
以上种种原因导致MAX的模拟机数量非常少
Because of all of this, very few 737 MAX simulators were made.
全球只有两家公司生产MAX的模拟机：CAE和TRU Simulation
Only two companies manufacture them: CAE and TRU Simulation.
这些模拟机不比真飞机便宜到哪去
These simulators are not a whole lot cheaper than the aircraft themselves.
一架737MAX全动模拟机价格估计在1500万美元左右
A full-movement 737 MAX simulator is estimated to cost up to $15 million
因此 运营一个模拟机的小时成本就要上千
and therefore the hourly cost to run one of these is in the thousands.
模拟机是很大很复杂的设备 用来精确模拟真飞机的飞行状态
They're just hugely complicated machines to develop to the level
that they accurately mimic the flight characteristics of a real aircraft.
精确度是很重要的 这样才能替代真飞机来进行训练
Accuracy is what is needed in order to use them for training in place of a real plane
否则算上燃料 航司的运营成本会高出更多
which, given fuel, cost airlines quite a bit more to run,
但MAX的模拟机需求很少 导致全球一共只有34台
but, given the little prior demand for 737 MAX simulators, only 34 exist worldwide.
我们假设 停飞的387架MAX需要5000名飞行员
Just, as an exercise, say 5,000 pilots are needed to fly the 387 grounded MAX aircraft.
模拟机上需要训练10小时 全球34台模拟机7×24小时不间断使用
If ten hours of simulator training are needed and every simulator in existence is used 24/7,
也需要整整两个月才能训练完这些飞行员
it would take two whole months to get those pilots trained.
现实中 飞行员基数只能更大 需要的训练时间更多
In reality, pilot numbers are likely larger, necessary training hours could be higher,
模拟机使用效率也会更低
and efficiency will be lower.
所以模拟机训练将是MAX复飞道路上最大的瓶颈
Simulator training will be a huge bottleneck to the reentry process.
很多运营MAX的航司自己买了模拟机 但还有很多航司没买
Many MAX operating airlines own their own simulators, but many others do not.
比如韩国的Eastar Jet航司就没有模拟机
For example, Eastar Jet, a South-Korean operator, does not
就需要另寻模拟机才能让他们的飞机重新上天
and therefore needs to find simulator availability in order to get their planes flying again.
对于有模拟机的航司
For the simulators owned by airlines,
他们肯定会优先给自家的飞行员训练用
their owners are undoubtably going to prioritize their own pilots for training first,
所以Eastar Jet可能很长一段时间内都找不到可用的模拟机
so those won't have availability for quite a while,
而对于有模拟机的大型训练中心
while among simulators owned by training centers,
他们肯定会优先服务像美国航空公司这种的大客户 而不是Eastar Jet这种小航司
these centers are much more likely to want to please a huge airline like American Airlines than tiny Eastar Jet.
所以很多没有模拟机的小航司就只能排在飞行员模拟机训练的“队尾”
Many of these smaller airlines are going to be at the end of a long list to get their pilots trained.
即使是大航司 也会想方设法把飞行员送到有模拟机的“天涯海角”
Even the big airlines will be sending their pilots to all corners of the globe to get simulator time.
比如斐济航空就有模拟机 航司也不大 很快就能训练完自家飞行员
Fiji Airways, for example, owns a simulator in Fiji and will quickly be able to train all their pilots,
所以其他航司都会排着队花重金去用斐济航空家的模拟机
and therefore other airlines are lining up to pay big money to use it.
类似情况的模拟机在冰岛 巴拿马等地也有
Other simulators with availability also exist in Iceland, Panama, and more,
所以航司会满世界找能提供模拟机训练小时数的地方
so airlines are scouring around the world for anyone who will give them hours.
不过当然了 这一切
This is all, of course, though,
还是要看FAA飞行标准化委员会对飞行员训练标准的决定
dependent on what exactly the FAA Flight Standardization board decides is required to train pilots.
认证流程中该阶段的决定一出
Sometime soon after the conclusion of that phase in the process,
FAA就会发适航指令
the FAA will issue an airworthiness directive.
这是MAX可以复飞的唯一指定官方实锤
This is the official order that says, for one, that the MAX can fly again,
而这也将是确定航司下一步决策的最终权威性文件
but it is also the final and definitive document outlining what steps airlines need to take
航司从中会得知MAX复飞需要的飞机改装与飞行员训练内容
in terms of aircraft modification and training so their specific aircraft and pilots can fly again.
但该指令并不意味着工作结束了 上百架停飞的飞机可以重返蓝天了
This directive, though, does not mean work is over and the hundreds of grounded aircraft can fly again.
实际上还差得远
Quite the opposite, in fact.
真正的好戏才刚开始
This is where the real work begins.
所有387架飞机都处于长期停放 荒废的状态
All of the 387 grounded aircraft have been just sitting there, largely abandoned.
让它们保持和航司机队中正常运营的飞机一样的维护状态将会花费巨额成本
Keeping them each in the same state of maintenance as an aircraft actively flying in a given airline's fleet
would be hugely expensive,
所以多数航司都只是放着 不维护
so most operators have largely left their aircraft be.
因此 每架飞机都要对所有系统和零件进行全面测试
Therefore, each aircraft needs to go through a process of testing all systems and components,
外加一些深度清洁工作 才能确保它们真的可以重新上天
in addition to a deep clean, to be sure they're truly ready to fly.
当然 它们还要安装波音的修复软件
They also, of course, need to have Boeing's revised software installed.
整套流程下来 每架飞机要花上两周时间
This whole process is expected to take, for each aircraft, up to two weeks.
一旦航司确定了MAX可以重新投入运营的大致时间
As soon as airlines know with relative certainty the timing of the MAX's reentry,
他们可能会重新分配资源 让尽可能多的机务投入到飞机的重新运营工作上
they're likely to shuffle resources around to dedicate as many mechanics as possible to aircraft reentry.
这可能会让其他飞机的大型维护遭到延期
That could mean delaying heavy maintenance on other aircraft.
波音自己更难受 他们要处理400多架飞机
Boeing will also have to go through an even more exhaustive process for the 400 or so MAX jets
这些飞机都是停飞后继续生产且还未交付的
that they built since the beginning of the grounding that now sit at their factories undelivered.
每一架飞机都是即将完成的状态
Each of these aircraft are at a stage just short of completion.
它们绝大部分已经完工 但在可以交付给客户之前还有大量工作要做
They're built, for the most part, but still significant amounts of work need to be done
before they're ready to be delivered to customers.
清理这些挤压的“存货”预计要花上一年
Clearing that backlog is expected to take about a year.
接着 航司还要安排MAX的复飞工作
Following this, airlines will need to rework the MAX into their schedules.
如果赶上最赚钱的暑运
If the reentry happens during the most profitable summer season,
那即使航司为了提升运力已经安排额外的航班 MAX方面的工作也得赶快
one could expect this to happen quite quickly,
possibly even with airlines scheduling extra flights given the extra capacity.
但如果赶上一年中不那么忙的时候
If its in the less busy times of the year, though,
那让MAX重新投入航司的运营时间表可能要花上一阵子
it could be a while before the MAX is fully reincorporated into airline schedules,
因为时间表有时是提前几年就安排好的
which are planned sometimes years in advance.
而现在最大的未知是 当MAX重新投入运营
The biggest unknown, though, happens when the MAX is back in service:
乘客会去坐这款饱受批评的飞机吗？
will passengers fly on the beleaguered aircraft?
历史的答案是 会
History says yes.
过去其他因为安全问题停飞的热门机型中
After other popular aircraft have been grounded in the past for safety reasons,
从来没有出现过消费者抵制某种机型的问题
there has never been a serious issue with a consumer boycott of the plane type,
不过话说回来 乘客相比之前几十年 可以获取的信息更多了
but passengers do have something that they didn't back decades ago in similar cases: information.
一方面 从未有过一款机型被停飞后受到媒体的广泛关注
For one, never has an aircraft grounding been such a media event.
另外 几十年前
In addition, before the last few decades,
机票通常是通过旅行社预订的
flight bookings typically happened through a travel agent
消费者通常不会提前知道他们的飞机型号是什么
and the consumer wouldn't really know which aircraft type they were booked on.
但如今 网络购票时网页会清楚显示乘坐机型
Nowadays, booking online, aircraft type is clearly displayed
因此 根据选项的不同 消费者可能会去坐MAX之外的其他飞机
and, given the choice, a consumer might choose to fly on other aircraft over the MAX.
最后 很多社交媒体也会跟着带节奏
Finally, social media has the power to escalate groupthink in such a situation.
一条乘客知道自己要坐MAX之后焦虑发作的短视频可能引起更大范围的恐慌
One video of a passenger having an anxiety attack
upon learning they're flying on a 737 MAX could go viral and cause mass anxiety.
波音也正为此做着准备
Boeing is preparing for all of this.
他们一直为解决从预订到飞行中乘客焦虑症而制定计划
They've been developing a plan for how to respond to passenger anxiety
anywhere from during the booking process to inflight.
计划包括监视社交媒体舆情
Part of the plan includes monitoring social media and,
且如果有乘客在乘机前或飞行中发布了对飞机的担忧
if a passenger is publishing concerns inflight or in the airport,
波音会进行在线回复 并通知机组相关个人的信息
responding to this digitally and notifying flight crew about the individual.
他们还计划让员工把带有飞机安全信息与改进内容的小卡片分发给焦虑的乘客
They also plan on having employees distribute small cards with information on the aircraft's safety
and the changes to anyone anxious,
还制作了详细说明视频 供那些想深入了解的人观看
in addition to creating explainer videos for those who want to learn more.
波音无疑也将花费大量资源开展公共宣传活动 以消除大众对该飞机的担忧
Boeing will also no doubt spend huge amounts of resources conducting a public information campaign
to quell concerns about the aircraft
毕竟如果乘客都不敢坐 那航司就不会买你的飞机
because, if passengers won't fly the aircraft, airlines won't buy it.
MAX复飞之事 诚波音危急存亡之秋也！
Truly everything is on the line for Boeing with this reentry.
MAX是波音的摇钱树 全波音都在围着它转
The aircraft is Boeing's cash cow and the entire company is centered around it.
以上描述的也都仅仅是计划
What's just been described is only the plan,
而一旦走错一步 就会满盘皆输
and if any step in it fails, then the entire process fails.
737MAX一路走来 计划里的事没办成几样
Few things have gone to plan with the 737 MAX so far,
所以对于波音来说 形势不容乐观
so the stakes for Boeing have never been higher.